Finding Aid for Kellogg African American Health Care Project Records 1918-2000
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Kellogg African American Health Care Project records 1918-2008
Kellogg African American Health Care Project.
5 linear feet
Project funded by the W.K. Kellogg Foundation to document the health care experiences of African Americans in southeastern Michigan consisting primarily of oral history interviews with African American health care practitioners and administrators covering the period 1940-1969, background files relating to the project, and oral history transcripts and tape recordings. Project funded by the W.K. Kellogg Foundation to document the health care experiences of African Americans in southeastern Michigan consisting primarily of oral history interviews with African American health care practitioners and administrators covering the period 1940-1969. Background files relating to the project, and 42 oral history interview transcripts and tape recordings. Interviews discuss biographical details, desegregation efforts in Detroit area hospitals, and social conditions facing African Americans.
9841 Bimu 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The records of the Kellogg African American Health Care Project (donor no. 8704 ) were received in 1998. A final accession was received in 2000.
No further additions to the records expected.
The record group is open for research.
In 1997, the University of Michigan's Historical Center for the Health Sciences received a $400,000 grant from the W.K. Kellogg Foundation to accumulate resources relating to African American health care in southeast Michigan in the 1940s to 1960s. The resulting oral history project contains valuable information regarding the issues of racial discrimination, labor and migration patterns and health care, and the attitudes of African Americans concerning the past health care system.
Even though black-owned hospitals were in existence during this period and African Americans served as health care professionals, information regarding the African American experience was not well documented or has not been retained. Researchers in charge of the project, Ronald Amos and George Myers, thought that the best remaining sources of information would come from the patients, doctors, nurses, and hospital administrators themselves. Representatives from the Detroit Urban League, the Detroit Medical Society, the National Association of Black Nurses, and other organizations also participated in the study.
Other components of the study include the accumulation of historical medical records, a Web site and CD-ROM relating to African American health care, and materials from two national conferences. The first conference, entitled "The First Conference on Health Care Experiences of African Americans in Southeastern Michigan: How the Past Affects the Future," was held on October 29, 1997, and featured speakers on topics such as a historic perspective on genetic screening programs for diseases commonly found only in the African American community, dementia care for African Americans, and the problems with managed care. A second National Conference, with the theme of "How the Past Shapes Today and Tomorrow," took place in February of 1999, at the Charles H. Wright Museum of African American History, and is also documented here. Its focus was the history and the effects in society today of segregated health care.
The project ended in the summer of the year 2000. An exhibit entitled "Helping Hands," featuring historic photos, documents, and articles on the African American health care experience in southeastern Michigan, continues to tour the Detroit area.
This record group does not contain the original documentation. Due to the importance of this study, several sets of records were created and were distributed to various archives, including the Walter P. Reuther Library at Wayne State University, the Burton Historical Collection at the Detroit Public Library, the Charles H. Wright Museum of African American History in Detroit, and the Center for Afro-American and African Studies at the University of Michigan-Ann Arbor. Much of the material as well as additional background and related information has also been posted to the project's web site, which is available at http://www.med.umich.edu/haahc/.
The records of the Kellogg African American Health Care Project have been kept in the original order in which they were received and have been divided into two chronological series: Phase I and Phase II, reflecting the two separate accessions that were received. The interviews in the Phase I series were conducted in 1997 and accessioned by the Bentley Historical Library in 1998, while the interviews in Phase II were conducted from 1997 through 1999 and accessioned by the library in 2000. Both of these series have a similar order and arrangement, differing mainly in who was interviewed; in addition, there is some updating of administrative papers in the 2000 accession. Both series are divided into two subseries: Administrative Files and Interviews. A description of the subseries for both of the series is below.
The Administrative Files subseries contains the organizational and background materials for the project including copies of the signed consent forms. This subseries gives several access tools for the interview portion of the collection as well as detailed information regarding the interview methodology. A Master Index and a Tape Index allow access by topic to both the transcripts and the tape-recorded material. Material related to follow-up research and further studies is also available.
The Interviews subseries contains the transcripts and tape recordings of the individual interviews. This subseries is organized alphabetically by the name of each person interviewed. A biographical sketch is provided for each individual and in some cases, copies of publications, photographs or computer-generated images of the participant, resumes, and news clippings are also included. In the Phase I series, the cassette tapes containing the interviews are included within each person's file. In the Phase II series, the tapes are stored separately.
List of Subjects Interviewed
Anderson, William G.
Ayala, Reginald
Boddie, Arthur W.
Brakefield-Caldwell, Wilma
Bryant, Jr., Henry Clay
Burton, Alice
Cain, Waldo L.
Collins, James W.
Cooper, Claude H.
Cooper, Vivienne B.
Dillard, Gladys B.
Gaines, Jr., George D.
Gant, Leon
Glass, Herman J.
Goodwin, Della M.
Harris, Joseph B.
Iacobell, Frank P.
Jefferson, Horace L.
Jenkins, Sidney B.
Johnson, Arthur L.
Keith, Rachel B.
Lawson, William E.
Love, Josephine H.
McCree, Suesetta
Maben, Jr., Hayward C.
Mason, Berna
Mottley, Dorothy
Northcross, Jr., David C.
Northcross, Ophelia B.
Peebles-Meyers, Marjorie
Raiford, III, Frank P.
Roberson, Jr., Rev. Garther
Roberson, Rev. Dr. S.L.
Smith, Elsie
Starks, Fannie L.
Swan, Lionel F.
Tanner, Natalia M.
Todd, Oretta Mae
Webb, Irma Clara
Whitten, Charles F.
Wright, Charles H.
Young, Watson
Subjects:
Kellogg African American Health Care Project.; African Americans--Michigan--Detroit Metropolitan Area.; African Americans--Medical care.; African American physicians--Michigan--Detroit Metropolitan Area.; African American nurses--Michigan--Detroit Metropolitan Area.; Discrimination in medical care.; Young, Watson.; Wright, Charles H., 1918-; African American dentists--Michigan--Detroit Metropolitan Area.; University of Michigan. Medical School.
Genre Terms:
Oral histories.
- Phase I
  - Administrative Files
    - Collection Inventory 1997 (Box 1)
    - Master Index 1997 (Box 1)
    - Master Tape Index 1997 (Box 1)
    - Project Description 1997 (Box 1)
    - Methodological Statement 1997 (Box 1)
    - Personnel 1997 (Box 1)
    - Training Guide and Appendices 1997 (Box 1)
    - Project Forms--Blank 1997 (Box 1)
    - Project Consent Forms--Signed 1997 (Box 1)
    - Background Articles 1963-1977 (Box 1)
    - Newsletter 1998 (Box 1)
    - Web Site 1998 (Box 1)
    - First Conference Brochure 1997 (Box 1)
    - Bibliography 1997 (Box 1)
  - Interviews
    - Ayala, Reginald
      - Interview Transcript 1997, 2 volumes (Box 1)
      - Oral Interview Guide 1997 (Box 1)
      - Curriculum Vitae (Box 1)
      - Publications/Manuscripts 1964 (Box 1)
      - Articles/Clippings 1969 (Box 1)
      - Cassette Tapes and Tape Index 1997, 4 tapes (Box 1)
    - Glass, Herman
      - Interview Transcript 1997 (Box 1)
      - Oral Interview Guide 1997 (Box 1)
      - Cassette Tapes and Tape Index 1997, 2 tapes (Box 1)
    - Harris, Joseph
      - Interview Transcript 1997 (Box 1)
      - Oral Interview Guide 1997 (Box 1)
      - Resume 1997 (Box 1)
      - Digital Images/Photographs 1939-1997 (Box 1)
      - Cassette Tapes and Tape Index 1997, 2 tapes (Box 1)
    - Johnson, Arthur
      - Interview Transcript 1997 (Box 1)
      - Oral Interview Guide 1997 (Box 1)
      - Resume 1996 (Box 1)
      - Cassette Tapes and Tape Indexes 1997, 3 tapes (Box 1)
    - Mottley, Dorothy
      - Interview Transcript 1997 (Box 1)
      - Oral Interview Guide 1997 (Box 1)
      - Digital Images/Photographs 1946-1951 (Box 1)
      - Cassette Tapes and Tape Index 1997, 3 tapes (Box 1)
    - Peebles-Meyers, Marjorie (Box 2)
      - Interview Transcript 1997 (Box 2)
      - Oral Interview Guide 1997 (Box 2)
      - Digital Images/Photographs 1982-1993 (Box 2)
      - Articles/Clippings 1968-1987 (Box 2)
      - Cassette Tapes and Tape Index 1997, 4 tapes (Box 2)
    - Smith, Elsie
      - Interview Transcript 1997 (Box 2)
      - Oral Interview Guide 1997 (Box 2)
      - Digital Images/Photographs undated (Box 2)
      - Cassette Tapes and Tape Index 1997, 2 tapes (Box 2)
    - Todd, Oretta
      - Interview Transcript 1997 (Box 2)
      - Oral Interview Guide 1997 (Box 2)
      - Digital Images/Photographs 1954-1964 (Box 2)
      - Cassette Tapes and Tape Index 1997, 3 tapes (Box 2)
    - Wright, Charles
      - Interview Transcript 1997 (Box 2)
      - Oral Interview Guide 1997 (Box 2)
      - Curriculum Vitae undated (Box 2)
      - Digital Images/Photographs 1970-1997 (Box 2)
      - Publications/Manuscripts 1964-1995 (Box 2)
      - Articles/Clippings 1985 (Box 2)
      - Correspondence 1997 (Box 2)
      - Cassette Tapes and Tape Index 1997, 2 tapes (Box 2)
    - Young, Watson
      - Interview Transcript 1997 (Box 2)
      - Oral Interview Guide 1997 (Box 2)
      - Digital Images/Photographs 1942-1997 (Box 2)
      - Cassette Tapes and Tape Index 1997, 3 tapes (Box 2)
- Phase II
  - Administrative Files
    - Collection Inventory 2000 (Box 3)
    - Master Index 2000 (Box 3)
    - Master Tape Index 2000 (Box 3)
    - Project Description 2000 (Box 3)
    - Methodological Statement 2000 (Box 3)
    - Personnel 2000 (Box 3)
    - Training Guide and Appendices 1997 (Box 3)
    - Project Forms--Blank 1997 (Box 3)
    - Project Consent Forms--Signed 1997-1998 (Box 3)
    - Background Articles 1955-1997 (Box 3)
    - Newsletter 1998, 2000 (Box 3)
    - Web Site 2000 (Box 3)
    - Second National Conference Brochure 1999 (Box 3)
      (includes two unlabeled photographs of conference participants)
    - Bibliography, c. 2000 (Box 3)
  - Interviews
    - Anderson, William
      - Oral Interview Guide 1998 (Box 3)
      - Curriculum Vitae (Box 3)
      - Articles/Clippings 1990 (Box 3)
      - Interview Transcript 1998 (Box 3)
      - Cassette Tapes 1998, 4 tapes (Box 5)
    - Boddie, Arthur
      - Oral Interview Guide 1998 (Box 3)
      - Digital Images/Photographs (Box 3)
      - Interview Transcript 1998 (Box 3)
      - Cassette Tapes 1998, 2 tapes (Box 5)
    - Brakefield-Caldwell, Wilma
      - Oral Interview Guide 1998 (Box 3)
      - Resume (Box 3)
      - Digital Images/Photographs (Box 3)
      - Interview Transcript 1998 (Box 3)
      - Cassette Tapes 1998, 3 tapes (Box 5)
    - Bryant, Jr., Henry
      - Oral Interview Guide 1998 (Box 3)
      - Digital Images/Photographs (Box 3)
      - Publications/Manuscripts: MIRLYN catalog record of publications (Box 3)
      - Articles/Clippings 1999 (Box 3)
      - Interview Transcript 1998 (Box 3)
      - Cassette Tapes 1998, 3 tapes (Box 5)
    - Burton, Alice
      - Oral Interview Guide 1997 (Box 3)
      - Digital Images/Photographs (Box 3)
      - Articles/Clippings 1953-1991 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence 1958-1981 (Box 3)
      - Interview Transcript (Box 3)
    - Cain, Waldo
      - Oral Interview Guide 1998 (Box 3)
      - Digital Images/Photographs (Box 3)
      - Publications/Manuscripts undated (Box 3)
      - Articles/Clippings 1955-1983, undated (Box 3)
      - Correspondence 1976, 1996 (Box 3)
      - Interview Transcript 1998 (Box 3)
      - Cassette Tapes 1998, 4 tapes (Box 5)
    - Collins, James
      - Oral Interview Guide 1998 (Box 3)
      - Curriculum Vitae (Box 3)
      - Digital Images/Photographs (Box 3)
      - Interview Transcript 1998 (Box 3)
      - Cassette Tapes 1998, 2 tapes (Box 5)
    - Cooper, Claude and Cooper, Vivienne
      - Oral Interview Guide 1998 (Box 3)
      - Digital Images/Photographs (Box 3)
      - Publications/Manuscripts 1976 (Box 3)
      - Articles/Clippings undated (Box 3)
      - Correspondence 1933, 1976 (Box 3)
      - Interview Transcript 1998 (Box 3)
      - Cassette Tapes 1998, 2 tapes (Box 5)
    - Dillard, Gladys
      - Oral Interview Guide 1998 (Box 3)
      - Digital Images/Photographs (Box 3)
      - Publications/Manuscripts 1997 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence 1944-1984, undated (Box 3)
      - Interview Transcript 1998 (Box 3)
      - Cassette Tapes 1998, 2 tapes (Box 5)
    - Gaines, Jr., George
      - Oral Interview Guide 1998 (Box 3)
      - Digital Images/Photographs (Box 3)
      - Interview Transcript 1998 (Box 3)
      - Cassette Tapes 1998, 2 tapes (Box 5)
    - Gant, Leon
      - Oral Interview Guide 1998 (Box 3)
      - Digital Images/Photographs (Box 3)
      - Interview Transcript 1998 (Box 3)
      - Cassette Tapes 1998, 3 tapes (Box 5)
    - Goodwin, Della
      - Oral Interview Guide 1998 (Box 3)
      - Resume (Box 3)
      - Digital Images/Photographs (Box 3)
      - Publications/Manuscripts (Box 3)
      - Articles/Clippings, 1991965-1973 and undated (Box 3)
      - Correspondence 1955-1993 (Box 3)
      - Interview Transcript 1998 (Box 3)
      - Cassette Tapes 1998, 3 tapes (Box 5)
    - Iacobell, Frank
      - Oral Interview Guide 1998 (Box 4)
      - Resume (Box 4)
      - Digital Images/Photographs (Box 4)
        (empty folder)
      - Interview Transcript 1998 (Box 4)
      - Cassette Tapes 1998, 2 tapes (Box 5)
    - Jefferson, Horace
      - Oral Interview Guide 1998 (Box 4)
      - Digital Images/Photographs (Box 4)
      - Articles/Clippings 1977-1978 (Box 4)
      - Correspondence 1947-1983 (Box 4)
      - Interview Transcript 1998 (Box 4)
      - Cassette Tapes 1998, 2 tapes (Box 5)
    - Jenkins, Sidney
      - Oral Interview Guide 1998 (Box 4)
      - Curriculum Vitae (Box 4)
      - Digital Images/Photographs (Box 4)
      - Publications/Manuscripts 1955-1973 (Box 4)
      - Articles/Clippings, 1991958-1981 (Box 4)
      - Correspondence 1959-1981, undated (Box 4)
      - Interview Transcript 1998 (Box 4)
      - Cassette Tapes 1998, 2 tapes (Box 5)
    - Keith, Rachel
      - Oral Interview Guide 1998 (Box 4)
      - Digital Images/Photographs (Box 4)
      - Correspondence 1976 (Box 4)
      - Interview Transcript 1998 (Box 4)
      - Cassette Tapes 1998, 2 tapes (Box 5)
    - Lawson, William
      - Oral Interview Guide 1998 (Box 4)
      - Resume (Box 4)
      - Digital Images/Photographs (Box 4)
      - Publications/Manuscripts 1997 (Box 4)
      - Articles/Clippings, 1971-1995 and undated (Box 4)
      - Correspondence 1916-1966, undated (Box 4)
      - Interview Transcript 1998 (Box 4)
      - Cassette Tapes 1998, 3 tapes (Box 5)
    - Love, Josephine
      - Oral Interview Guide 1998 (Box 4)
      - Digital Images/Photographs (Box 4)
      - Articles/Clippings 1967 (Box 4)
      - Correspondence (Box 4)
      - Interview Transcript 1998 (Box 4)
      - Cassette Tapes 1998, 2 tapes (Box 5)
    - Maben, Jr., Hayward
      - Oral Interview Guide 1998 (Box 4)
      - Curriculum Vitae (Box 4)
      - Digital Images/Photographs (Box 4)
      - Articles/Clippings 1966 (Box 4)
      - Interview Transcript 1998 (Box 4)
      - Cassette Tapes 1998, 3 tapes (Box 5)
    - Mason, Berna
      - Oral Interview Guide 1998 (Box 4)
      - Resume (Box 4)
      - Digital Images/Photographs (Box 4)
      - Articles/Clippings 1976-1979, undated (Box 4)
      - Correspondence 1933-1976, undated (Box 4)
      - Interview Transcript 1998 (Box 4)
      - Cassette Tapes 1998, 2 tapes (Box 5)
    - McCree, Suesetta
      - Oral Interview Guide 1998 (Box 4)
      - Curriculum Vitae (Box 4)
      - Digital Images/Photographs (Box 4)
      - Publications/Manuscripts 1997 (Box 4)
      - Articles/Clippings, 1958-c. 1964 (Box 4)
      - Correspondence 1994-1998 (Box 4)
      - Interview Transcript 1998 (Box 4)
      - Cassette Tapes 1998, 2 tapes (Box 5)
    - Northcross, Jr., David
      - Oral Interview Guide 1997 (Box 4)
      - Digital Images/Photographs (Box 4)
        (includes photographic prints)
      - Articles/Clippings, 1949-1956 and undated (Box 4)
      - Correspondence 1918-1979 (Box 4)
      - Interview Transcript 1997 (Box 4)
    - Northcross, Ophelia
      - Oral Interview Guide 1998 (Box 4)
      - Digital Images/Photographs (Box 4)
      - Articles/Clippings undated (Box 4)
      - Correspondence undated (Box 4)
      - Interview Transcript 1998 (Box 4)
    - Raiford, III, Frank
      - Oral Interview Guide 1998 (Box 4)
      - Digital Images/Photographs (Box 4)
      - Articles/Clippings 1956 (Box 4)
      - Interview Transcript 1998 (Box 4)
      - Cassette Tapes 1998, 2 tapes (Box 5)
    - Roberson, Jr., Rev. Garther
      - Oral Interview Guide 1998 (Box 4)
      - Digital Images/Photographs (Box 4)
      - Articles/Clippings 1994-1997 (Box 4)
      - Correspondence 1983 (Box 4)
      - Interview Transcript 1998 (Box 4)
      - Cassette Tapes 1998, 3 tapes (Box 5)
    - Roberson, Rev. Dr. S.L.
      - Oral Interview Guide 1998 (Box 4)
      - Digital Images/Photographs (Box 4)
      - Articles/Clippings 1981-1997 (Box 4)
      - Correspondence 1983 (Box 4)
      - Interview Transcript 1998 (Box 4)
      - Cassette Tapes 1998, 2 tapes (Box 5)
    - Starks, Fannie
      - Oral Interview Guide 1998 (Box 5)
      - Digital Images/Photographs (Box 5)
      - Correspondence 1974 (Box 5)
      - Interview Transcript 1998 (Box 5)
      - Cassette Tapes 1998, 2 tapes (Box 5)
    - Swan, Lionel
      - Oral Interview Guide 1997 (Box 5)
      - Digital Images/Photographs (Box 5)
      - Publications/Manuscripts 1963-1997 (Box 5)
      - Articles/Clippings 1965-1997 (Box 5)
      - Correspondence 1988-1993 (Box 5)
      - Interview Transcript 1997 (Box 5)
    - Tanner, Natalia
      - Oral Interview Guide 1998 (Box 5)
      - Digital Images/Photographs (Box 5)
      - Articles/Clippings 1957-1996 (Box 5)
      - Interview Transcript 1998 (Box 5)
      - Cassette Tapes 1998, 3 tapes (Box 5)
    - Webb, Irma Clara
      - Oral Interview Guide 1998 (Box 5)
      - Digital Images/Photographs (Box 5)
      - Interview Transcript 1998 (Box 5)
      - Cassette Tapes 1998, 2 tapes (Box 5)
    - Whitten, Charles
      - Oral Interview Guide 1998 (Box 5)
      - Curriculum Vitae (Box 5)
      - Digital Images/Photographs (Box 5)
      - Articles/Clippings 1976 (Box 5)
      - Interview Transcript 1998 (Box 5)
      - Cassette Tapes 1998, 2 tapes (Box 5)